We went through the practice for sets, tuples, and dictionaries, as well as the practice for
logic and functions. After lunch, we're going to review loops and the exercises for loops.
I feel like I am doing a pretty good job today because I think everybody is back.
So y'all like what you are learning and you're sticking around for the long haul. So
super thrilled about that. Now, before a kick things off, does anyone have any
quick questions that are not related to the exercises because I'm going to be going through those with you?
Now, all right, you're all Python experts. Awesome. Do my job.
Let's talk about sets, tuples, and dictionaries.
This is the practice that you should have gone through. So let's take a look.
Starting the Python Ripple, we remember that in order to create in empty set,
if we check for the type of my set, it's going to be a dictionary. So we create an empty set
by calling the set constructor. empty list is just two brackets. empty dictionary is
two curly braces. In empty tuple is parentheses with a sorry empty tuple is
one set of parentheses, a tuple with one item in it has a comma and a empty set is created by
using the set constructor. Remember that lists sets and dictionaries are mutable.
Tuples are immutable. If you need a shortcut to figure out if an item is mutable or not,
you can pass it into the hash function. So a hash of an empty tuple has a value hash of an
empty dictionary. Sorry, an empty set does not have a value hash of an empty dictionary does not
have a value and a hash of an empty list does not have a value. Those are all unhashable types
because they are mutable and they can be changed while if we check the hash for an integer or the
hash for a string. Those do have values because they are immutable. Now remember that for a set,
every item in that set needs to be unique. So if I have a list of names that has some duplicates in it
and I pass these into the constructor for set to make them into a set that set is only going to
have two values in it. Sets don't have order. So this order is not guaranteed. That also means
that I cannot ask for the zero with item. Sorry, I need to make a variable here.
Call this my names set. I cannot ask for the zero with items in a set.
Algan error that says the set object is not subscriptable. That means that it does not have an order
to it. That also means that I cannot change values in my set at for example the zero index.
The set object does not support item assignment. We talked a little bit about tuples.
Tuples need to have that comma if they only have one value.
You type that correctly. Something else that you might see that is valid Python syntax,
but I recommend against using it is you can actually create these tuples without the
parentheses around them. So I can say my tuple is equal to one and a comma.
This is valid syntax in Python. If I check the type of my tuple, it's a tuple. I can take a look at it.
I very much recommend that you do not do this and that you be as explicit as possible.
That's because this can be the source of a lot of really weird errors when you have a function
you're passing an arguments to it. Each argument is on its own line with that trailing comma.
Let's say you're doing a little bit of refactoring and you pull out one of those arguments
onto its own line to make it a variable and you forget to remove this trailing comma.
Now it's a tuple. You are an expecting a tuple, but you got a tuple and even recently this is
the kind of bug that has just bitten me for hours because I'm looking at it and this
comma is just invisible in my brain and I'm not understanding why I'm getting this error about
tuples when I'm not seeing the tuple. So I recommend always being explicit and adding those parentheses
around your tuples. Now we talked about how you can unpack tuples so if you have a student
and the student has a name and an age and a favorite subject and a GPA. Let's say John is about
student. We can use tuple unpacking to grab multiple values out of this tuple all at once so we
can say name, age, subject, GPA is equal to student and now I will have all of those variables defined.
If I do not have a match between the number of variables on the left hand side with the number
of values in the tuple, this is going to blow up with an error that says too many values to unpack.
Remember when you are doing any sort of unpacking like this, remember this error you will probably
be seeing a bit as you go through Python code and now you can just zero in to exactly what that means.
If there is a variable that we don't care about saving to use later can use this anonymous
underscore to say, hey, here's a placeholder so that I have the right amount of variables on
the left side of the expression. I don't care about saving it though and now I don't have that value error.
We talked about dictionaries and how dictionaries are defined with the curly braces and the
columns. So I can say that my dictionary has a key separated by a colon and then the value.
And I cannot access items in a dictionary by position because dictionaries do not have an order.
They only have keys. So if I tried to ask my dictionary for something at position zero,
doesn't know what that is. I'm just going to get a key error.
If we wanted to add new items to our dictionary, we can do that with the square bracket notation.
So if I wanted to get back the value at key, I would use the square bracket notation.
But unlike a list where I was passing in a position, instead I will pass in a key that is in the
dictionary and I will get back that value for the key. If I wanted to update that value in place,
I could just use the equals to assign a value to it. And now if I looked in my dictionary,
I would see that the value has been overwritten. If I wanted to check to see if a key was in
my dictionary, I would use the N key word. So I can say key in my dict and that will return true
or not a key in my dict and that will return false. Remember that lists are mutable. You can change
them. So if I had a list here, I can say that my list at zero is not now going to be negative 99.
And that will go ahead and change it. Dictionaries are also mutable. So I can say my dictionary
at key equals some other value and that works just fine. Sets are also mutable. So if I had
a set here, I can use the dot add operator to add a new item to the set to balls not mutable.
So if I have my student, I can get the value at position zero because tuples do have an order.
In fact, that order is very, very important. But they are not mutable. So if I try to change the
name here, I'm going to get an error because the tuple object does not support item assignment.
So all of these have different purposes. They all have different pluses, minuses, advantages,
and scenarios. I recommend that you spend some time reading Python code and that will give you
a better understanding of which data type is best used when. And also while you're learning
referring back to the cheat sheets, because those are going to give you hints about mutability
about how to access objects about order and about what methods you can use on these different objects.